Henry Mosler
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Henry Mosler papers
1856-1929
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Mosler, Henry
4.5 linear feet
The papers of painter Henry Mosler (1841-1920), who began his career in Cincinnati, Ohio, lived in Germany and Paris for at least 2 decades, and finally settled in New York, measure 4.5 linear feet and date from 1856-1929. The collection documents Mosler's life and career through biographical material, personal and professional letters from members of the military, museums, family, friends and colleagues, writings including an 1862 Civil War diary, personal business records, printed material, artwork and sketchbooks, and photographs of Mosler, his family, colleagues and artwork.
Provenance
The bulk of the collection was donated to the Archives of American Art by J. F. McCrindle, a great-grandson of Mosler, in 1976 and 1977, having been previously lent to AAA for microfilming. A photograph album was donated in 1993 by Paul M. Hertzmann, a dealer who acquired it through purchase. Additional materials were donated in 2008 and 2009 by McCrindle via John T. Rowe, president and CEO of the Joseph F. McCrindle Foundation.
Alternative Forms Available
The collection was digitized in its entirety in 2012 and is available on the Archives of American Art's website.
Restrictions on Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Biographical Note
Henry Mosler (1841-1920) worked primarily in Ohio, New York City, and Europe as a painter of portraits and scenes of rural life in Europe. Mosler served as an artist correspondent for Harper's Weekly during the Civil War.
Born in Silesia (Poland) in 1841, Henry Mosler immigrated to New York City with his family in 1849. In the early 1850s the family moved to Cincinnati, Ohio, where Mosler received art instruction from James Henry Beard, becoming an accomplished portrait painter and an active participant in the Cincinnati art scene.
Following the outbreak of the Civil War in 1861, Mosler became an artist correspondent for Harper's Weekly, documenting the Western Theater in Kentucky and Tennessee. He served as a volunteer aide-de-camp with the army of Ohio from 1861-1863 and was present at the engagement at Green River, and "present and under fire" at the battles of Shiloh and Perryville.
Immediately thereafter, Mosler relocated to Dusseldorf for two years and attended the Royal Academy, followed by six months in Paris where he studied with painter Ernest Hébert. In 1866 Mosler returned to Cincinnatti where his portraits and genre scenes enjoyed growing popularity.
In 1875 Mosler traveled to Munich and two years later settled in Paris from where he enjoyed critical and financial success both in Europe and in the United States. Mosler was known for his genre paintings of peasant life in rural Brittany and he became a regular participant in Salon exhibitions and won honorable mention in the Salon of 1879, when his painting Le Retour, became the first work by an American artist to be purchased by the French government. In 1888 he won the gold medal at the Paris Salon and in 1892 he was made chevalier de la Legion d'Honneur and officier de l'Académie.
Mosler returned to the United States temporarily during this period, including a trip in 1885-1886 to visit the West and collect material for paintings of Native American life.
In 1894 Mosler returned to the United States and settled in New York, where he became a popular teacher and an active participant in the New York art scene. In 1895 he was made an associate member of the National Academy of Design, and in his last decades took up landscape painting during summers in the Catskill mountains, and produced genre paintings depicting scenes from colonial and rural life. Mosler continued to enjoy widespread popularity until his death in 1920.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of painter Henry Mosler (1841-1920), who began his career in Cincinnati, Ohio, lived in Germany and Paris for at least 2 decades, and finally settled in New York, measure 4.5 linear feet and date from 1856-1929. The collection documents Mosler's life and career through biographical material, personal and professional letters from members of the military, museums, family, friends and colleagues, writings including an 1862 Civil War diary, personal business records, printed material, artwork and sketchbooks, and photographs of Mosler, his family, colleagues and artwork.
Biographical material includes passports for Mosler's travel during the Civil War and to the American West in 1875-1876, as well as identification cards and awards from Mosler's years in Germany and Paris, including the Ordre National Légion d'Honneur awarded to him in 1892.
Letters record Mosler's service as an aide-de-camp for the Army of Ohio and his activities as an artist correspondent for Harper's Weekly from 1861-1863 in the Western Theater of the Civil War. However, the bulk of the letters document Mosler's career from the 1880s onward. Found are letters from museums, art associations, government agencies including the Minsistere de l'Instruction Publique et des Beaux-Arts, and colleagues in Europe and the United States including artists James Henry Beard, Julien Dupré, Gabrier Ferrier, Ernest Hébert, William Henry Howe, William Ordway Partridge, and Leon Germain Pelouse, among others. There are also scattered letters from Mosler.
Writings and notes include an 1862 Civil War diary and two illustrated notebooks from 1862 and 1863 containing sketches, and travel and financial notes. Also found are two biographical accounts of Mosler's career and poems by various authors, many inspired by Mosler's paintings.
Personal business records include an account book documenting Mosler's income and expenses from 1869-1878 and 1886-1892, and Library of Congress copyright certificates for four of Mosler's pictures.
Printed material documents Mosler's career in the United States and Europe through news clippings, a brochure, and an exhibition catalog for an 1897 exhibition of his paintings at Galleries of Pape Bros.
Artwork and sketchbooks include six sketches and an engraving by Mosler, and two books containing sketches by Mosler and other artists including James Henry Beard. The series also contains one ink drawing each by Leon Germain Pelouse and E. Hillery.
Photographic material includes albums and individual photographs of Mosler in his studio and with others including his immediate and extended family, and students. Also found are photos of artists including Gabriel Ferrier, Ernest Hébert and Thomas Buchanan Read, Brigadier General R. W. Johnson and opera singers Emma Nevada Palmer and Renée Richards. Photographs of artwork are primarily found in 2 oversized albums dedicated by Mosler to his children, Edith Mosler and Gustave Henry Mosler respectively.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 7 series:
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1863-1892, 1921 (Box 1, OV 10; 4 folders)
Series 2: Letters,1861-circa 1920 (Boxes 1-2; 1.3 linear feet)
Series 3: Writings and Notes, circa 1860-circa 1900 (Boxes 2-3, 6; 0.4 linear feet)
Series 4: Personal Business Records, 1869-1905 (Box 3; 4 folders)
Series 5: Printed Material, circa 1860s-1929 (Box 3; 10 folders)
Series 6: Artwork and Sketchbooks, 1856-1917 (Box 4, OVs 10-11; 0.5 linear feet)
Series 7: Photographic Material, 1860-circa 1910 (Boxes 5-9, BV 12; 2.0 linear feet)
Names and Subject Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following terms:
Subjects:
Ferrier, Gabriel, 1847-1914; Hébert, Ernest, 1817-1908; Read, Thomas Buchanan, 1822-1872
Subjects-Topical:
Artists' studios--Photographs; Expatriate painters--France--Paris; Painters--New York (State)--New York
Subjects-Geographical:
United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Journalists; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Personal narratives
Types of Materials:
Diaries; Drawings; Illustrated notebooks; Photographs; Sketchbooks; Sketches
Names:
Beard, James Henry, 1812-1893; Dupré, Julien, 1851-1910; Ferrier, Gabriel, 1847-1914; Flameng, François, 1856-1923; Hébert, Ernest, 1817-1908; Howe, William Henry, 1846-1929; Partridge, William Ordway, 1861-1930; Pelouse, L. G. 1838-1891
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Biographical Materials, 1863-1892, 1921, Series 1:; (Box 1, OV 10; 4 folders)
  Identification cards include: an 1864 entrance card for the Dusseldorfer Kunstler-Verein Malkasten, a card for the Konigl Akademie der bild Kunste in Munich, 1875-1876, a Carte D'Exposant for the Exposition Universelle of 1889, with a photograph of Mosler, and Mosler's 1892 Ordre National Légion d'Honneur. Passports are for 1863, requesting Mosler's safe passage during the Civil War, and for 1874, for his travel to the American West. Also found is a 1920-1921 entry for Mosler in Who's Who in America, an inoculation certificate for Ida Mosler, and a lock of hair.
  This series has been scanned in its entirety.
  - Identification Cards and Notes, 1864-1892, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Inoculation Certificate and Lock of Hair, 1876, circa 1880s (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Ordre National de la Légion d'Honneur, 1892, (oversized material housed in OV 10) (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Passports, 1863, 1874, (oversized material housed in OV 10) (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Ordre National de la Légion d'Honneur, 1892, (oversized material scanned with Box 1, F3) (Box OV 10)
  - Passports, 1863, 1874, (oversized material scanned with Box 1, F4) (Box OV 10)
- Letters, 1861-circa 1920, Series 2:; (Boxes 1-2; 1.3 linear feet)
  Letters are primarily written to Mosler with scattered letters written by him. Of particular note is a letter to his parents written from 3 miles outside Corinth, Mississippi on 22 May 1862 in which he describes the scene during the Siege of Corinth following the Battle of Shiloh.
  Calling/congratulation cards were sent in response to Mosler's winning the gold medal at the Paris Salon in 1888 and being awarded the Ordre National Légion d'Honneur in 1892.
  Correspondents include members of the military regarding his service in 1861-1863 and can be found in several places. A folder of Civil War letters includes Brigadier General R. W. Johnson's request for Mosler to serve as aide-de-camp, and a March 1863 letter from a friend (Bradley?) encamped at Murfreesboro and referring to the building of fortifications there following the Second Battle of Murfreesboro. Letters from Harper's Weekly include a summary of Mosler's military service from 1861-1863 and a handwritten account of his experiences in September 1861 in and around Louisville, Kentucky. Also found are letters from the United States Army and the Department of the Interior in 1885 introducing Mosler as a "distinguished artist" visiting the West. Included are 3 letters from General Philip Sheridan in which he refers to the "indians, in their uncivilized state," and Mosler's desire "to be able to depict them in a correct light."
  Other letters are from museums and art associations, Mosler family members, including Mosler's children, artist Gustave Henry Mosler and Edith Mosler, friends and colleagues including artists James Henry Beard, Julien Dupré, Gabriel Ferrier, François Flameng, Ernest Hébert, William Henry Howe, Heinrich Mücke (history painter and Mosler's Düsseldorf professor), J. Francis Murphy, William Ordway Partridge, and Leon Germain Pelouse, among others. Letters from the Ministere de l'Instruction Publique et des Beaux-Arts include the 1879 purchase certificate for Mosler's painting Le Retour, and a letter assigning the painting to the Luxembourg Museum.
  Letters from the Military Order of the Loyal Legion of the United States confirm Mosler's election as a Member-at-Large to the order in 1896. Also found is a list of autographs of Cincinnati Artists representing a petition to suggest that the Cincinnati Museum purchase Mosler's painting The Last Moments.
  Many of the letters are in French and German.
  See Appendix for Extended List of Correspondents from Series 2
  The bulk of the series is arranged alphabetically by correspondent in general files or in named files if there are 5 or more letters from an individual correspondent. A group of files arranged by subject can be found at the beginning of the series.
  Appendix: Extended List of Correspondents from Series 2
  This appendix is taken from an existing list compiled at some point after the collection was accessioned and is intended to assist in identifying correspondents, as many signatures are difficult to decipher or illegible. Completeness and accuracy of the list cannot be guaranteed.
  Abraham, Victor Emmanuel
  Adan, Emile
  Aldine, Publishing Co.
  Allis, Edward Phelps
  Avery, Samuel P.
  Bail, Joseph
  Bailly-Blanchard, Col.
  Barria, J. (?)
  Bartlett, Paul
  Bartell, Prof. V.
  Bassier, Cabinet du Ministre
  Bates, Harry, Godey Co.
  Bauerle, Carl
  Beard, Dan
  Beard, James Henry
  Beau, Alfred
  Beer, F.
  Benedite, Leonce
  Bigelow, C. B., American Art Association
  Bodkin, Charlotte
  Boulanger, Gen.
  Bournand, François
  Bourne, George
  Bradley, L. P.
  Breton, Jules
  Bridgman, F. A.
  Brispot, Henri
  Brozik, Vacslav
  Buhler, F. Zuber
  Burgers, H. J.
  Butler, E., Cincinnatti Art Club
  Cabanel, Alexandre
  Cabinet du Ministre
  Carl-Rosa, Mario
  Cauffman, Sig. J.
  Chamberlin, W. H., Loyal Legion
  Chambre des Deputes
  Champney, J. Wells
  Church
  Cincinnatti Commercial Office
  Ckenbracher (?), T.
  Cleveland, Lucy
  Collins, M.
  Constant, Benjamin
  Corrington (?), John
  Cortissoz, Royal
  Courtois, Gustave
  Crefeu, Etienne
  Cramer, Mary (letter of introduduction to President Ulysses S. Grant)
  Crawrford, Emily
  Cummings, Dorothy
  Dagnan, P.A.J.
  Dal-, Leon
  Dameron, E.
  Danzinger, Rosa
  Davis, Charles (?)
  Davis, Margaret S.
  de Campan, P.
  De Chavannes, P.
  de Czachorski, Ladislas
  de Lambert, Marguerite
  de Luce, Percival
  de Mun, Albert
  d'Almeida, W. B.
  D'Ozouville, A.
  deJean, A.
  Delabbe (?), A.
  Dennis, W. J.
  Dessar, Louis
  Dix, M. (?), miniature painter
  Dodge, Harrison H.
  Doubouchet, G.
  Dougan, D. H.
  Drapeau, Le
  Du Nimes (?), Renee
  Dubouchet, M./Mme.
  Dupain, Edmund
  Dupre, Julien
  Dustin, Silas S. (?)
  Dyer, Charles Gifford
  Ech-, A.
  Edgar, Oscar
  Ehrich, Louis R.
  Erefey (?)
  Ezekiel, Moses-Jakob
  Faber, L. E.
  Ferrier, Gabriel
  Fertiault, François
  Field, painter
  Flameng, François
  Fleury, J. (?) Robert
  Fleury, Jean
  Ford, Sheridan
  Frebauly (?)
  Fuster, Charles
  Ga-, Jules
  Galland, Bertha
  Gardner, Elisabeth
  Garnier, Edouard
  Garvier (?), Edward
  Gatineu
  Goshorn, A. S. (Director Cincinnati Museum Association)
  Gross, P. A.
  Guay, Gabriel
  Guillaumet, P.
  Guygellion, Louise (?)
  H-, Edumnd
  Halsted, W.
  Hardeman, Elizabeth
  Haquette, Georges
  Harper & Bros.
  Harper's Weekly
  Hartmann, Sad-
  Hassaurek, Frederick
  Haven, Daisy
  Haymes, H.
  Healy, G.P.A.
  Hébert, Ernest
  Henger, Thomas E. (?)
  Henry, Edward L.
  Hoebel, Arthur, New York Times
  Homer, W. H.
  Hooper, Lucy
  Howe, W. H.
  Hustin, M./Mme.
  Ingalls, M. E.
  Iwill
  Jacob, Stephen
  James, Maj. F. B. (Military Order of the Loyal Legion of the United States)
  Jansen, P.
  Joergens
  Johnson, Brigadier General R. W.
  Jordan, D. M.
  Kaplan, A. O.
  Kauffmann, S. H. (?), Corcoran
  Knight, Ridgway
  Knoedler, R. F.
  Kroyer (?), F.
  Kuhn
  L-ington, W.P.L.
  Lamar, L.Q.C., Secretary of the Interior (letter of introduction)
  Lasoniere
  Lassaille, M.
  Lau-, Frederick S.
  Laugee, Georges
  Le E-, L. M.
  Le Leusche, L. M. (?)
  Le Roux, Hector
  Lee
  Lefebvre, Jules
  Leighton, Frederic
  Leipziger, H. M.
  Leisten (or Leister), Jacobus
  Leunier (?)
  Lhermitte, Leon
  Loyal Legion of the United States
  Miles, Roger
  Mabel-Trevor, Helen (?)
  MacPherson, G. G.
  Madden, Thomas
  Maignan, Albert
  Marks, Montague
  Masson, Charles, Ministere de l'Instruction Publique
  Mayer, Henry
  Mayers, Nathan
  Mayers, C.
  Mehaus, C. H. (?)
  Meikie (?), H.
  Melchers, Gari
  Merson, Luc Olivier
  Mielziner, Leo
  Mieuer, D. J.
  Miller, Juanita
  Miller, L. W., Art Club of Philadelphia
  Ministere de l'Instruction Publique et des Beaux-Arts
  Ministere des Affaires Etrangeres
  Moch, M. E.
  Mocker, Melchior
  Moeselagen, F.
  Moeselagen, J.
  Moffat, W. D.
  Morris, A. K., YMCA
  Morton, Levi Parsons
  Moses, Otto A.
  Moses-Jacob, Ezekiel
  Mosler, Agnes
  Mosler, Edith
  Mosler, Gustave
  Mourges, Robert
  Moyes
  Mücke, Heinrich
  Mullin, Alex J.
  Murphy, J. Francis
  Neal, David
  New York Herald
  Nicoll, J. C., National Academy of Design
  Niehaus, Charles H.
  Noble, S.
  Noble, T. S.
  Nontet, D.
  Ollendorf, Gustave
  Paine, H. G., Harper's Weekly
  Palmer, Ray
  Panhauts, C. M. (?)
  Partridge, William Ordway
  Pearce, Charles Sprague
  Pelouse, Leon Germain
  Pengelly, W. G.
  Petitjean, E.
  Peixotto
  Picknell, William L.
  Pleinpent (?), F. B.
  Plimpton, C. A.
  Porral, Jules
  Profesional Photographer's Society of New York
  Race, G. F.
  Rae, Alison
  Rea, John S.
  Read, Thomas Buchanan
  Reid, J. (?)
  Rettig, John
  Richards, Renée
  Reid, Robert S.
  Rongier, Jeanne
  Rosenberg, H.
  Rosenthal, Albert
  Rosenthal, Toby E.
  Roth, Th. (?)
  Royal Academy (invitation)
  Ruze, Adolphe
  Sherard, Robert (?)
  Saile, Fernand
  Saint-, G.
  Sardey, V.
  Sayler, Nelson (letter of introduction)
  Schatz, Joseph L.
  Schaus, W (?)
  Scribe, Fernand
  Seissen, F. (?)
  Sh-, R. M.
  Shearard, Robert M.
  Simmons, Sallie M.
  Skinnner, Otis
  Smillie, George
  Smith, Rufus H.
  Stanhope
  Stanton, Theodore
  Surand, Gustave
  Thierot, J. H.
  Thompson, Harry
  Thouron, Henry
  Townsend, George Alfred
  Trebaulz, T.
  Trioche, Gen.
  Turner, C. Y.
  Turner, Henry
  Turquel, Edmund: see Ministere de l'Instruction Publique et des Beaux-Arts
  Turquet, Henry
  Turquet, M.
  Turquet, Octavie
  United States Army, Sheridan, Lt. General Philip Henry (letters introducing Mosler)
  United States Department of the Interior (letters introducing Mosler)
  Vanderstraeyen, L.
  Vaul, Eugene
  Vauthier, Pierre
  Vele-, Gustave
  Vey-, J.
  Vezin, Charles
  Vidal, E.
  Vignaud, Henry
  Volksblatt, Cincinnati
  von Catharin, D. (from Henry Mosler)
  von Piloty, Carl
  Vonnoh, Robert W.
  Voruz, E.
  Vower, J.
  Wameron, Peter
  Watrous, H. W.
  Wattson, A. Francis
  Webber, C. T.
  Weeks, E. L.
  Whistler, J. McNeill (1 calling card)
  Wight, Moses
  William, Moses
  Wismile, William
  Worms, Henry
  Worms, Ida
  Wright, M.
  Y-, Edmond
  Zein
  Zuber-Buhler
  - Calling/Congratulation Cards, 1888 April (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Calling/Congratulation Cards, 1892 July (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Empty Envelopes, circa 1860s-circa 1920 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Empty Envelopes, 1884-1902 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Illegible Signatures, circa 1863-1892 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Illegible Signatures, 1893-1895 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Illegible Signatures, 1896-1917 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - List of Autographs of Cincinnati Artists, 1890 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - A, General, circa 1877-circa 1917 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - B, General: Ba, circa 1888-circa 1909 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - B, General: Be, 1886-1910 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - B, General: Bo-Bu, 1886-1909 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - C, General: Ca-Ci, circa 1873-circa 1910 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - C, General: Cl-Cu, 1873-1916 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Civil War Letters, circa 1861-1863 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Constant, Benjamin, 1886-1893 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - D, General: Da, 1889-1916 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - D, General: De-Di, 1883-1917 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - D, General: Do-Dy, 1882-1917 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - de Czachórski, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Dubouchet, H., circa 1888-circa 1899 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Dupré, Julien, 1888-1908 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - E, General, 1888-1908 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - F, General, circa 1876-circa 1893 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Ferrier, Gabriel, circa 1883-1912 (Box 1, Folder 29-30)
  - Fertiault, F., 1884-1902 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Flameng, François, circa 1910-circa 1912 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Fuster, Charles, circa 1892-circa 1908 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - G, General, circa 1888-1908 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - H, General, circa 1885-circa 1892 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Harper's Weekly, 1861-1863, 1895 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Hassaurek, Frederick, 1885 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Hébert, Ernest, circa 1880s-1913 (Box 1, Folder 38-39)
  - Howe, William Henry, circa 1890-1898 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - I, General, 1888-1889 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - J, General, circa 1889-1917 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - K, General, 1892-1917 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - L, General, circa 1888-1911 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Lefebvre, Jules, circa 1880s-circa 1900 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - M, General: Ma., 1892-1903 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - M, General: Me, circa 1891-circa 1896 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - M, General: Mi-Mu, circa 1880-1916 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Military Order of the Loyal Legion of the United States, 1895-1905 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Ministère del'Instruction Publique et des Beaux Arts, circa 1866-1929 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Mosler Family, circa 1885-circa 1894 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Mosler, Henry, 1862, 1893, 1902 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Murphy, J. Francis, 1895-1896 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - N, General, 1895-1914 (Box 1, Folder 54)
    (includes letter from Mosler to the New York Herald)
  - O, General, circa 1892 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - P, General, 1867-1899 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Partridge, William Ordway, 1896-1904 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Pelouse, Leon Germain, circa 1880-1884 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - R, General, 1863-1910 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - S, General: Sa-Se, 1884-1901 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - S, General: Sh-Si, 1885-1896 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - S, General: Sk-Su, 1888-1904 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - T, General, 1865-1899 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Townsend, George Alfred, circa 1896-1897 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - U, General (United States Army, Department of Interior etc.), 1885-1893 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - V, General, 1876-1917 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Vidal, E., circa 1891-1892 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - W, General, 1879-1897 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Webber, C. T., 1885-1903 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Worms, Henry and Ida, 1888-1916 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Y-Z, General, 1889, 1892 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Writings and Notes, circa 1860-circa 1900, Series 3:; (Boxes 2-3, 6; 0.4 linear feet)
  Of particular note in this series is Mosler's 1862 Civil War diary (with transcript) and two illustrated notebooks, 1862 and 1863, containing diary entries, poems, sketches, financial tallies and names and addresses. The diary contains records of sketches Mosler made for Harper's Weekly, a narrative of his activities during 1862, financial notes, poems, names and addresses, and several sketches.
  Writings by others include biographical accounts of Mosler's life: a Historical Press Association typescript entitled "Henry Mosler, Genre Painter," and a handwritten account of Mosler's career by an unidentified author. Also found are handwritten poems, many of them dedicated to Mosler and/or inspired by his paintings and with accompanying notes and letters. They include poems by J. C. Beard, William J. Dennis ("My Eighty-Third Christmas"), Oscar Edgar (3 poems), François Fertiault (10 poems), Charles Fuster, Alice C. Hall, Roger Miles (2 poems), Berthe Nordez, and Thomas Buchanan Read. Also found is the poem "Acrostic" written by Lt. H. Millard at Shiloh in 1862.
  - By Mosler (Box 2)
    - Civil War Diary, 1862 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Civil War Diary Transcript, of 1862 item (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Illustrated Notebook, 1862 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Illustrated Notebook, 1863 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Notes and Poem (possibly by Mosler), circa 1860s-circa 1880s (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - By Others (Box 3)
    - Biographical Accounts of Mosler's Life, circa 1900, circa 1921 (Box 3, Folder 4)